Phd, Post doctoral Bioinformatics - Evolutionary Biology & Ecology University of Brussels

Natalia de Souza Araujo

souza.nataliaa@gmail @nat2bee http://natevolution.com ORCID 0000-0002-0074-6844

My main research interests rely on combining molecular biology and bioinformatics to answer evolutionary questions. Recent studies include: molecular mechanisms of heat adaptation in ants; gene conversion events in complete genomes of bovines cohorts; genetics mechanism involved in the evolution of social behaviour; and identification of genes involved in bee parasitic interactions.

EDUCATION

- **2012-2017** *Ph.D. in Genetics and Evolutionary Biology University of São Paulo*Expression of Genes Involved in Social Behaviour in Bees with Different Levels of Eusociality. Advisor: Maria Cristina Arias
- **2010-2012** *M.Sc. in Genetics and Evolutionary Biology University of São Paulo*Analyses of the *Anastrepha fraterculus* complex (Diptera: Tephritidae) in Brazil based on mitochondrial cytochrome oxidase I sequences. Advisor: Andre Luiz Paranhos Perondini
- **2006-2010** B.Sc. in Biological Science Universidade Paulista
- **2004-2007** Technician in Chemistry Escola Técnica Estadual Getúlio Vargas

LANGUAGE and PROGRAMMING SKILLS

- Portuguese (native); English (IELTS 7.0); Spanish (basic); French (intermediary)
- Python; R and Unix Environment

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

- **2019-current** Bioinformatics // Evolutionary Biology & Ecology ULB, University of Brussels (research supervisors: Dr. Serge Aron and Dr. Matthiew Defrance)
- **2017-2019** Unit of Animal Genomics GIGA, University of Liège (research supervisors: Dr. Michel Georges and Dr. Carole Charlier)
- **2012-2017** Laboratory of Genetics and Evolution of Bees, University of São Paulo (research advisor: Dr. Maria Cristina Arias)
- **2014-2015** Laboratory of Ants, evolution & genomics, Queen Mary University of London (research advisor: Dr. Yannick Wurm)
- **2010-2012** Laboratory of Evolution and Genetics of True Fruit Flies, University of São Paulo (research advisor: Dr. Andre Luiz Paranhos Perondini)
- **2008-2010** Laboratory of Evolution and Histophysiology, University of São Paulo (research advisor: Dr. João Carlos Shimada Borges UNIP)

ADVISING

- **2018-current** Paulo Cseri Ricardo Expression of Genes Related to Parasitic Behaviour in Bees. *Co-advisor in PhD Research*
- **2015-2018** <u>Larissa Logullo Piconi</u> Gene Expression Analyses of Behavioural Candidate Genes in Native Bees. *Co-advisor in undergraduate Research*

FUNDINGS

- **2019** PACBIO, SMRT Leiden Travel Grant [International]
- **2016** Society for the Study of Evolution Travel Grant [International]
- **2013-2017** FAPESP Regular Ph.D. Fellowship [National]
- 2014-2015 FAPESP BEPE Ph.D. Fellowship Abroad [National]
- **2010-2012** CNPQ Regular M.Sc. Fellowship [National]
- **2008-2010** CNPQ/ UNIP PIBIC Fellowship for undergraduate students [National]
- **2006-2010** PROUNI Scholarship for graduation costs [National]

AWARDS

- **2016** ICE 2nd Place for Best Student Poster. Session: Genetics and Evolutionary Entomology
- **2016** Brazilian Congress of Genetics Honourable Mention for Participation in the Francisco Mauro Salzano Graduate Student Award of Evolution
- **2014** IUSSI 3rd Place for Best Student Poster
- **2011** 57° Brazilian Congress of Genetics Honourable Mention for Participation in the Graduate Student Oral Award of Animal Genetics
- **2009** Instituto Biológico Scientific Merit for Oral Presentation

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS and PRESENTATIONS

- **Araujo, N.S.** and Arias M.C. (2019) Mitochondrial genome characterization of *Melipona bicolor*: Insights from the control region and gene expression data. Gene.
- Araujo, N.S.; Wurm Y.; Schmitz B.; Arias M.C. (2018) Unveiling the expression dynamics of genes involved in bee sociality. IUSSI Symposium invited speaker –
- Santos, P.K.F; <u>Araujo, N.S.</u>; Françoso, E.; Zuntini, A.R.; Arias, M.C. (2018) Diapause in a tropical oil-collecting bee: molecular basis unveiled by RNA-Seq. BMC Genomics.
- <u>Araujo, N.S.</u>; Santos P.K.F.; Arias M.C. (2018) RNA-Seq reveals that mitochondrial genes and long noncoding RNAs may play important roles in the bivoltine generations of the non-social Neotropical bee *Tetrapedia diversipes*. Apidologie.
- <u>Araujo, N.S.</u>; (2017) Expression of genes involved in the social behaviour of bees with different levels of eusociality. [PhD thesis]. São Paulo: University of São Paulo, Instituto de Biociências
- <u>Araujo, N.S.</u> and Arias, M. C. (2017) DNA methylation and the evolution of bee eusociality. Evolution 2017 Talk.
- <u>Araujo, N.S.;</u> Wurm Y.; Arias M.C. (2016) Worker Subcastes: What makes bees nurses? IUSSI-NAS Colloquium Talk.
- **Araujo, N.S.**: Zuntini A.R.; Arias M.C. (2016) Getting Useful Information from RNA-Seq Contaminants: A Case of Study in the Oil-Collecting Bee *Tetrapedia diversipes* Transcriptome. OMICS: A Journal of Integrative Biology. 20(8), 491-192.
- Arias, M.C. et al. (2016) Microsatellite records for volume 8, issue 1. Conservation Genetics Resources. 1(8), 43-81.
- <u>Araujo, N.S.</u> and Borges J.C.S. (2015) Rodlet cells changes in *Oreochromis niloticus* in response to organophosphate pesticide and their relevance as stress biomarker in teleost fishes. International Journal of Aquatic Biology.